<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The trumpet of the Lord sounded, and his sword drawn, and the separation made between the precious and the vile; and the vineyard of the Lord dressed by his own husbandmen, and the dead trees cut down, and all the mystery of witchcraft discovered in all professions: by them who have come thorow great tribulation, whose garments have been washed in the blood of the lamb; who are accounted as the off-scowring of all things for Christs sake, scornfully called by the world Quakers.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84829</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E732_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118244</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84829)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118244)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 113:E732[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The trumpet of the Lord sounded, and his sword drawn, and the separation made between the precious and the vile; and the vineyard of the Lord dressed by his own husbandmen, and the dead trees cut down, and all the mystery of witchcraft discovered in all professions: by them who have come thorow great tribulation, whose garments have been washed in the blood of the lamb; who are accounted as the off-scowring of all things for Christs sake, scornfully called by the world Quakers.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the black Spread-eagle neer the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to George Fox.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April. 8th. 1654".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118244:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRUMPET Of the LORD SOUNDED, And his SWORD drawn, And the Separation made between the Precious and the Vile; AND The Vineyard of the Lord dreſſed by his own Husbandmen, and the dead trees cut down, and all the myſtery of Witchcraft diſcovered in all Profeſſions:</p>
            <p>By them who have come thorow great tribulation, whoſe garments have been waſhed in the blood of the LAMB; who are accounted as the off-ſcowring of all things for Chriſts ſake, ſcornfully called by the World QUAKERS.</p>
            <q>And the angel thruſt in his ſickle into the earth, and gathered the vine of the earth, and caſt it into the great wine-preſs of the wrath of God. And the wine-preſs was troden without the city, and blood came out of the wine-preſs even to the horſe bridles, by the ſpace of a thouſand ſix hundred furlongs. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 14.19, 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black Spread-eagle neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118244:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118244:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H all you that do profeſs God and Jeſus Chriſt in words, ſee what you do poſſeſs of him. All pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion without poſſeſſion, is nothing but hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and diſſimulation. You have heard long, and profeſſed much in words: but now <hi>it is not the hearers, but the doers that ſhall be juſtified.</hi> For <hi>he that ſaith he loves God and Chriſt, and keeps not his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is a lyer, and the truth is not in him. If you love me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>keep my commandments.</hi> Now I command you to <hi>love one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, with the ſame love that I loved you withal.</hi> By this you may ſee how you are brought into the obedience of the truth. <hi>Love the Lord with all thy heart, and thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> Thou muſt love the Lord with thy hearty love: ſee if thou do ſo: If thou ſay thou doſt, and doſt not, he knows thy heart, and he will judge thee for thy hypocriſie. Take heed that thou be not found a lyer before him. Thou that art in the higheſt profeſſion, ſee if thy heart be not abroad in the world, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf in pleaſures, or pride, or profit, or wantonneſs, or anger, or wrath, or peeviſhneſs, or perverſneſs, or covetouſneſs, or delighting in ſporting, or idle talking, or fooliſh jeſting, or ſpeaking evil of that thou knowſt not: take heed that thou be not delighting thy ſelf in ſwearing and lying, and drinking, and running a whoring after other lovers. If thy heart love any thing above the Lord, or delight in any thing but in him alone, he knows thy heart, and he will judge thee for diſſembling with him: for if thou ſay thou loveſt the Lord, and liveſt in envie, wrath, backbiting, deceit, oppreſſion, cruelty, or guile, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or hard-heartedneſs, or paſſionateneſs, or any of theſe, the Lord knows the ſecrets of all hearts; act it never ſo cloſely, or ſubtilly, it is naked and bare before the Lord, who is preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verywhere, and his eyes are open to behold the good and the evil. Thou mayſt make a profeſſion of God and Chriſt, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118244:3"/>make a fair ſhew to the world, and yet be an hypocrite: but if thy heart and tongue be not one, God doth know it, and he will judge thee for it: and if thou make never ſuch a ſhew in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, and ſeem never ſo righteous, and do not bridle thy tongue, thy Religion is vain. <hi>Pure religion and undefiled is this, before God and the Father, To viſit the fatherleſs and widow, and to let the oppreſſed go free, and to keep thy ſelf unſpotted in the world.</hi> Now if thou make a profeſſion in words, and a ſhew, to be ſeen of men, and do not the works that are required, as to <hi>depart from iniquity,</hi> and to <hi>live righteouſly, holily, and uprightly in this preſent world,</hi> all thy profeſſion is but hypocriſie, and God will judge thee and plague thee for it. Thou hadſt better never have made profeſſion of God and Chriſt, then to profeſs him, and live in ſin and wickedneſs. Where is thy love to him, when thou diſobeyeſt him, and breakeſt his Commandments? There is no love to him, there is none at all to him, if thou do ſo; but on the contrary, thy love is to the devil: for, <hi>know you not, that his ſervant you are to whom you obey? whether it be of ſin unto death, or of obedience unto righteouſneſs.</hi> Now if thou obey righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thou art ſervant to it, and art free from ſin: but if thou obey ſin, thou art ſervant to ſin, ſerving the devil, and ſo art free from righteouſneſs: then where is thy profeſſion?</p>
            <p>The Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt is to <hi>redeem</hi> ſouls <hi>from their vain converſation.</hi> See what you are redeemed from, if you be not yet in your ſins: if you be, you are enemies to him. The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of Jeſus Chriſt is a Miniſtery of love, and joy, and peace in the holy Ghoſt. It is a glorious Miniſtery, not formal, but ſpiritual. You that profeſs it, ſee that you put in practice what you profeſs: if thou profeſs thy ſelf to be a Chriſtian, obey the commands of Chriſt; make manifeſt the fruits of thy Miniſtery. Be not a fore-ſayer, but I charge thee by the Lord that thou put in practice, or elſe profeſs nothing at all. If thou do profeſs love, and do not perform it, what is thy profeſſion worth? Doſt thou clothe the naked, doſt thou feed the hungry, doſt thou let the oppreſſed go free? If thou doſt not, thou art not obedient to the commands of Chriſt. Doſt thou love thy enemies, doſt thou bleſs them that curſe thee, doſt thou pray for them that hate thee, and deſpightfully uſe thee? Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Swear not at
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118244:3"/>all:</hi> doſt thou ſo? He ſaith, <hi>Go not to law:</hi> doſt thou not? <hi>Let your converſation be without covetouſneſs:</hi> is it ſo? He ſaith, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence no man evil for evil:</hi> doſt thou ſo? He ſaith, <hi>Vengea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce is mine, and I will repay it:</hi> doſt thou obey him, and keep his ſayings? If thou do not, what uſe is thy profeſſion of? It grieves the Spirit of the Lord, to ſee the well-favoured harlot, how ſhe ſits in the ſtreet, deceiving the ſimple, and enſnaring them; and how ſhe is painted with the Saints words, and with Chriſts, and profeſſes 'tis love to him, and perſecutes him to death, where he is made manifeſt in his people. She ſits as a Queen, but ſhe muſt come down and ſit in the duſt ere long: and you muſt all give an account of your profeſſion, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t fruits you have brought forth. For the Lord is coming to ſeparate the ſheep from the goats, and your works will be tried, whether your love be made man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>feſt or no: He will ſay, <hi>Come, ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you: when I was hungry, you fed me; when I was thirſty, you gave me drink; when I was naked, you clothed me; when I was ſick in priſon, you viſited me.</hi> They will ſay, <hi>When did we ſee thee ſo?</hi> Yea, ſaid he, in my members ye did: for <hi>inaſmuch as ye did it to them, yet did it to me.</hi> Here are the fruits of the righteous. Now the Lord is coming to look for fruit, ſee that your fruit be good that you bring forth, I mean ye that are profeſſors: for if it be not good, it will not be accepted; for <hi>every tree that brings not forth good fruit, muſt be hewn down, and caſt into the fire.</hi> Your works muſt be tried by the fire; and if they be unrighteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, they muſt with the trees be caſt into the lake that burneth. See if ye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Commandments of Chriſt, or of the Devil. The carnal heart ſaith, God is <hi>an hard Maſter:</hi> but he is not: it is none but the evil and ſlothful ſervant that ſaith ſo: for he is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, <hi>his commandments are not grievous,</hi> but joyous: The carnal heart ſaith it is hard to keep them. But where is thy love towards him, when thou doſt diſobey him? When he ſaith, <hi>If ye love me, keep my commandments;</hi> the carnal ones ſay, It is hard to keep the commandments of the Lord, but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils commandments are eaſie; they can keep them with eaſe, and go on in joy and delight: it is no trouble to keep the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils commandments. Saith he, You may be proud, it is but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118244:4"/>Decencie: he ſaith you may be covetous; it is but a provident care: he ſaith you may be angry; it keeps others in ſubjection to you: he ſaith you may be drunk; it is but good-fellowſhip: he ſaith you may be oppreſſors; it will bring you in gain: and he ſaith you may uſe deceitful merchandiſe; for if you do not as the world do, ye ſhall loſe by them: he ſaith you may ſwear and lye; they will believe you the better: he ſaith you may be envious, and hate; or elſe they will not matter for you. And ſo in every unrighteous act, he will make a cloak for it, to cover it. And for to live in unrighteouſneſs it is very eaſie: you may run on the broad way to deſtruction with joy and delight: but to act in righteouſneſs it is very hard. And then you ſay the way is narrow to keep in it: it is ſo; therefore if ever you come to Sion, you muſt go on the ſtrait way: for, it <hi>is the ſtrait way that leadeth to life, and few there be that finde it;</hi> but <hi>broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be that follow it. Let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt, depart from iniquity:</hi> for, <hi>no unclean thing ſhall enter into the kingdom of heaven:</hi> for <hi>he is of purer eyes then to behold iniquity.</hi> Therefore <hi>perfect holineſs in the fear of the Lord;</hi> and live not in words, but bring forth fruits meet of amendment of life; and ceaſe from evil, and turn to the Lord, that he may have mercy upon you. <hi>If you be willing and obedient, you ſhall eat the good of the land:</hi> but if you be diſobedient and ſtiff-necked, then wo and miſery will be your portion: for the day of the Lord is coming in power, and he will gather his elect unto himſelf. See if you can yet witneſs your election, that your names may be written in the book of Life: if ye cannot, ye are deceived already: then what uſe is all your profeſſion of? it will prove hypocriſie; and it were better never to have made a profeſſion, then to profeſs and not put in practiſe what you profeſs. For it is not they that ſay they love God and Chriſt, but they that make their love manifeſt by their works, that ſhall be accepted, by yielding up obedience to his Commands. If you ſay you love God and Chriſt, in words, and your actions be contrary, it is but hypocriſie. You may profeſs much in words; but if your hearts be not one with your tongues, to guide them; though they may propheſie in his Name, yet if they be workers of iniquity, they muſt depart;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118244:4"/>and Chriſt will ſay, <hi>Depart, ye workers of iniquity; I know you not.</hi> Therefore be not ſayers, but doers, and be what you ſpeak in all things; and do not ſpeak one thing, and do another: for God doth love the upright in heart. See how you are built up into the truth: for the Saints that ſpake forth the Scriptures were what they ſpake, and they ſpake what they lived in: they were <hi>the workmanſhip of God, created in Chriſt Ieſus to good works.</hi> See if you can witneſs this yet: ſee what you are wrought out of, and what ye are wrought into. And live not in words, but bring forth fruit, that God may be glorified, that you may be what you profeſs in reality. For the day of the Lord is coming, wherein the deceits ſhall be laid open, and all things made manifeſt, as it is: all ſecrets ſhall be revealed, the ſecrets of all hearts. And all the crowns of men ſhall be thrown down: for <hi>how can ye believe, which ſeek honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour which is of God alone?</hi> All the haughtineſs of man ſhall be brought down, and all the loftineſs of men laid low: all ſecret pride, and ſecret envie, and ſecret malice, and ſecret revenge, and ſecret ſubtilty, and ſecret hypocriſie, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret diſſimulation, ſhall be laid open, and made manifeſt; and they ſhall all be aſhamed of the evil of their doings, and the pure naked truth be unveiled and ſpread abroad, that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may flouriſh, and ſee the Lord ſet up and honoured, and rule and reign for evermore. The Lord will plague the Beaſt, and judge the Whore, and puniſh the wicked very ſore. Sing Hallelujah to the Higheſt for ever.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>A Separation betwixt the people of God, the righteous ſeed, that ever ſuffered with the ſeed of evil doers, that each may know that witneſs, and ſee ye have a cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, who are the ſeed of the righteous; and you may ſee you have a cloud of witneſſes who are the ſeed of evil doers, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the righteous ſeed. Prieſts, People, and Rulers, you know the letter ſpeaks, and you may read it in <hi>Matthew,</hi> and all along the Scriptures, how the Prieſts, People, and Rulers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118244:5"/>were againſt Chriſt: in which generation you ſhew your ſelves to be; and clear your ſelves for the generation of the feed of the righteous. Do not you hale out of your Synagogues, and hale before Magiſtrates? Do not you here fulfil Scripture, which Chriſt propheſied of? Do not you impriſon, which Chriſt ſpeaks of? Do not you ſtone with ſtones, ſhewing your ſelves to be in the generation that ſtoned <hi>Steven,</hi> that cryed againſt the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? <hi>Acts</hi> 7. And do not you hale and beat them that come to ſpeak the truth freely in your Temple, ſhewing your ſelves openly to be in that generation that beat the Apoſtles, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them out of the Temple? And do not your Teachers go <hi>in the way of Balaam, for gifts and rewards,</hi> who had the ſpirit of errour, ſhewing ye have erred from the truth? Do they not go <hi>in the way of Cain,</hi> to envie, who would murder? And do you not ſcorn, and mock, and wonder, and deſpiſe, as they did againſt <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the ſervants of God? Are not your Teachers they that Chriſt ſpeaks of, which ſaid, <hi>Beware of the Scribes and Phariſees, which ſtand praying in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and have the chiefeſt places in the aſſemblies, called of men Maſters, devouring widows houſes?</hi> Are not all your Teachers ſuch which Chriſt cryed wo againſt? Are not you ſuch, and your generation, that ever perſecuted the righteous ſeed, who had the form and the colour, but not the power? That generation perſecuted Chriſt and the Prophets, which is the ſeed of evil doers, a generation that is wiſe in their own eyes, a generation that is ſwift to ſhed blood; the ſame generation that perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Martyrs in nature. You cry out of your fathers mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyring, how Queen <hi>Mary</hi> impriſoned and burned: you are in the ſame nature. It was the generation that held up the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Temple, the outward Worſhip, that ever perſecuted. Prieſts and People, Where did any of the Apoſtles ſtone any, perſecute any, or impriſon any, or cauſe any to be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or haled before a Magiſtrate? Oh horrible! how dare you profeſs Chriſt, and walk in the doctrines of devils? Where did Chriſt give any ſuch command to act any ſuch thing? You take him for your cloak, and talk of his blood, who are mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, blood-ſuckers, hunting after blood, to devour the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſeed, as all your fathers did in all ages, in the time of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118244:5"/>in the time of <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> in the time of <hi>David,</hi> in the time of the Apoſtles: they ſtoned, they impriſoned, punched, and beat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And theſe be all your witneſſes, and they be your fathers who acted before you, who had gotten the form of words, as you have. Here be ye witneſſes that ye are the ſame generation in nature, and have your cloud of witneſſes which ever perſecuted the righteous ſeed, as you daily make it manifeſt. Both Prieſts, Rulers, and People, this I am moved of the Lord to write unto you, to let you ſee your ſelves: for you have not learned Chriſt at all. For we have a cloud of Witneſſes which were ſtooed by your generation, as you may read in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and in divers places; they were ſtoned, mocked. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſtoned for denying the outward Temple; <hi>Steven</hi> was ſtoned to death, who denied the outward Temple: <hi>John</hi> was baniſhed: they took up ſtones to ſtone Chriſt the righteous ſeed: And where Chriſt is made manifeſt, you do ſo now. <hi>Christ to day, yeſterday, and for ever.</hi> Praiſes, praiſes be to the Lord God Almighty for ever. Our ſuffering is our joy, our reproach is our riches. Search the Scriptures, and you will finde it to be ſo.</p>
               <p>Do not your Prieſts cry, <hi>Murder them?</hi> Do not your People cry, <hi>Stone them?</hi> Do not you wag your heads at them? Do not you gnaſh your teeth at them which you call Quakers? <hi>Moſes</hi> quaked, <hi>David</hi> quaked, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſhaked, who cryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prieſts. You may as well cry, <hi>Stone Moſes, Paul, David, Jeremiah,</hi> and the reſt of the holy men of God who quaked and trembled, as they who witneſs quaking, who quaked and trembled as they who witneſs quaking now, as they did then. Here you ſhew your ſelves to be the ſeed of blood-ſuckers thirſting after blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118244:6"/>
               <p>O Ye blood-ſuckers, which hunt after blood, which lay traps and ſnares to ſlay the righteous! Oh what a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is this you live in, that are ſo full of fury and rage! ſome mocking, ſome beating, ſome plotting and lying in wait to ſhed the innocent blood: and yet you dare make a profeſſion of God and Chriſt. Chriſt never taught that doctrine. And there you ſhow your ſelves to be as bloody perſecutors as ever the Jews were, who crucified Chriſt, and ſought to ſlay the Apoſtles. Oh <hi>England, England,</hi> is this the fruit of thy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, that your vineyard bears which you have planted? How, ye vine-dreſſers; how is the vine yard full of briers and thorns! Oh how is the vineyard full of dead trees, which cumber the ground, and bring forth no fruit! Oh how are the Springs ſtopped, which ſhould water it, with the Philiſtims! Oh how full is the vineyard of Serpents! Oh how full is the vineyard of thiſtles and nettles! Oh how full is the vineyard of weeds? Oh how full is the vineyard of wilde beaſts, and of trees that bear wilde grapes, and ſowre grapes, which ſet the childrens teeth on edge! Oh, time hath been, and now is, that the pretended Dreſſers and Lookers to the vineyard are blinde, and do not know one tree from another, and cannot diſtinguiſh a Lamb from a Dog, a Sheep from a Goat, a Dove from a Kyte. Full is the vineyard of wolves, ſtrong horſes neighing, and the horſes of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his chariots whirring up and down: and the vineyard is full of theeves and robbers, and full of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, drunk with the wine of the ſowre grape. The Land is full of Oathes, and mourns becauſe of ſuch. The fleſh hath been defiled: the Land is full of reſpecting of perſons. But now is the Lord ariſing, and riſen, which reſpects no mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and lays the ax to the root of the trees; every one that brings not forth good fruit, muſt be hewn down, and caſt into the fire. For now is the Lord ſending his ſons, and daughters, and ſervants into the vineyard. Spears are broken, and turned into mattocks and plow-ſhares, and ſwords into pruning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooks. Some are plowing up, and ſome are hacking up, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118244:6"/>ſome are pruning, and ſome are dividing the ſheep from the goats, and the lambs from the wolves, making a diſtinction, putting a difference; and ſome are bridling their horſes which have been wilde: ſome are diſtinguiſhing the Kytes from the Doves, and putting a difference between the precious and the vile, betwixt the holy and unholy. Tremble, ye mountains and hills, before the Lord: for out of Sion doth the Lord ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his voice. Wo, wo to all you who inhabit the earth: you will be ſcattered as the winde ſcatters the chaff; you will be conſumed as the fire conſumes the ſtubble: for the mighty day of the Lord is coming, that ſhall burn as an oven: look upon an oven when it is burning, and you are afraid to go into it: but the fire of the Lord is coming, which will burn you all up, root and branch. The mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, who will perform his word, and none of you that are proud and wicked can eſcape it: whether you will hear, or whether you will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, the Word of the Lord ſhall ſtand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>TO all you who profeſs the Scriptures to be your Rule and Touch-ſtone to try withal, who fine men becauſe they will not put off their hats at your Seſſions, at your Aſſizes, at your Courts. When did any of the heatheniſh Kings or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates in any Age ſet up ſuch a Law? Read the Chronicles thorow, and give an example, elſe you ſhew your ſelves to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip all the heatheniſh kings. When did ever <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was a Judge over all Iſrael, command any people that came before him to put off their hats, and fine them if they would not bow to him? Or where did ever <hi>David</hi> or <hi>Solomon,</hi> who were Kings, command any to put off their hats which came before them, and fine them if they would not do it? Here you ſhew your ſelves, that you outſtrip all the heatheniſh Kings, who had not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Law from God; and the righteous Kings, that had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Law from God. The Law ſaith, Thou ſhalt not bow down to any but the Lord God: though there was a time when <hi>Jacob</hi> bowed to <hi>Eſau,</hi> and there was a time when <hi>Iſrael</hi> bowed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118244:7"/>to <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> and there was a time when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was deſtroyed and his hoſt, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſung over <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> muſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> then bow to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> when he is deſtroyed? Then came the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God, when Iſrael was brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſaying, Thou ſhalt not bow down to any creature. For he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects perſons, tranſgreſſeth this Law. Many will bow to great men, that have a great deal of earth, and fine apparel; but not to a poor man, that hath not fine apparel: and there he is a tranſgreſſor of the righteous Law: for who reſpects perſons, commits ſin. And there was a time when <hi>Haman</hi> made a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and who would not bow to him might be hanged: and the true Jews, who had received the righteous Law of God, could not bow to him. And there was a time when <hi>Haman</hi> was hanged upon his own Gallows. And there was a time when <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> made an Image, and all that would not bow to it, were caſt into the firy furnace: and there was a time his kingdom was rent, and the Image, whoſe head was gold, whoſe breſt was ſilver, whoſe belly and thighs were braſs, whoſe legs were iron, whoſe feet were part iron and part clay, the Stone cut out of the mountain without hands, ſtrikes at the feet of the Image, and he comes to be hewn down. But <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> cannot underſtand this dream, but <hi>Daniel,</hi> who was a trembler, underſtood the ſtone, and the watcher, and ſaw the Kingdom and Dominion that endures for ever: he ſaw <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s kingdom, who would have all bow to him, become as the graſs that withers away. So adieu all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ones, who ſtumble at this corner-ſtone.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>WE are accuſed to deny the Scriptures. The Scriptures do we not deny: the holy men of God ſpake them forth as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt: and they were given forth by inſpiration of the Spirit; and they are of no private interpretation: they were not given forth by the will of man. They that gave forth the Scriptures, were ſuch as ever ſuffered
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118244:7"/>by the ſeed of evil doers, and teſtified againſt them: therefore the ſeed of evil doers muſt be kept out of the Scriptures, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cut: They that ſpoke them forth, judged the ſeed of evil doers, and kept them out. All who had the life of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and ſet them forth, cryed againſt ſuch as bare rule by their means. The Scripture ſpeaks againſt them: they muſt be kept out of the Scriptures. Such as jangle about the Saints conditions, ſuch as ſeek for gain from their quarters, and are hirelings, and ſeek for the fleece, they did not give forth the Scriptures; but ſuch as cryed againſt theſe, gave forth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; and all who have the life of the Scriptures, as they had who gave them forth, teſtifie againſt ſuch now, as they did then: and ſuch muſt be kept out of the Scriptures. And ſuch as go in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and after the errour of <hi>Balaam</hi> in covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, did not give forth the Scriptures: who had the life of the Scriptures, teſtified againſt ſuch, and kept them out of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures: and ſo all who have the life of the Scriptures now, muſt keep ſuch out of the Scriptures now. <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſlew <hi>Baal.</hi> And all ſuch as were called of men Maſter, ſtood praying in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, had the choiceſt places in the Aſſemblies, uppermoſt rooms at Feaſts, laid heavie burdens upon the people, gave not forth the Scriptures: keep ſuch out of the Scriptures: for who had the life of the Scriptures, teſtified againſt ſuch. And all ſuch as deny perfection, and overcoming of ſin, are Miniſters of Antichriſt; they di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not give forth the Scriptures: keep ſuch out of the Scriptures: for who had the life of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, teſtified againſt ſuch, and kept them out. Holy men of God ſpake forth the Scripture, and teſtified againſt all ſin and imperfection. All ſuch as buy and ſell the Saints words, and make a trade of the Prophets, Chriſts, and his Apoſtles words, muſt be kept out of the Scriptures; for they wreſt and pervert it, and make people believe they are gifted, whenas the gift of God is not to be bought and ſold for money: keep ſuch out of the Scriptures; for they are lyers, evil beaſts, and ſlow-bellies, falſe prophets, and ſuch as deny the light, that ſay Chriſt hath not enlightned every one that cometh into the world; who go about to make Chriſt a lyer, and a falſe Prophet: ſuch keep out of the Scripture; for they are lyers, and falſe Prophets, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118244:8"/>Dreamers: who had the life of the Scriptures, kept ſuch out; and who have the life of the Scriptures, keep out ſuch now. Here you dwell clear and pure, in true judgement, and know what to receive. The life which gave forth the Scriptures, that life muſt ſpeak them forth again. All ſubtil Serpents keep out of the Scriptures: who had the life, kept them out, teſtifies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, though they applied <hi>Abrahams</hi> words, who were not of <hi>Abraham:</hi> he who was the life, kept them out of the Scripture: and now, all who apply the Prophets and Apoſtles condition, Chriſts words, and have not life, ſuch muſt be kept out for ever. All ſuch who have the life of the Scriptures, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſimplicity and innocencie, and they put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the holy and profane, clean and unclean, and what was polluted, and what was not polluted; and what was torn, and what was holy: they were not to eat what died of it ſelf. All who are in the firſt birth, born of the fleſh, gave not forth the Scriptures: ſuch were perſecutors of them who are born of the Spirit: ſuch keep out of the Scripture, for they are enemies to that which gave out the Scriptures, ſo are to be kept out of the Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>OH doth not ſomething in you cry a voice for equity, for equity, to ſet open the door of equity? The Innocent cries for the law of equity, which reſpects no mans perſon, how much of the earth he hath, or how little; equity reſpects neither, but equity: for, <hi>the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs of it.</hi> When the door of Equity is ſet open, then mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces the ſimple ones. Oh therefore hearken to Equity, and that which cries for it in your hearts and conſciences, and ſo break the bands by ſhewing mercy. And while Iniquity rules, Equity is oppreſſed and priſoned, and the luſtful nature rules, which croſſes Equity for its own ends, to gather in riches to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on heaps, ſome by cozening, or lying, or cheating. And
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118244:8"/>all theſe things Equity cries out of thee, and tells thee of all thy actions privately, when thou art by thy ſelf, and when thou art publike. Equity cries for juſtice and righteouſneſs, and againſt all ſin, and ſwearing, and lying, and adultery, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſnes, and drunkenneſs: for this deſtroys honeſty and reaſonableneſs. And Equity cries in all your hearts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences for equity: for it is burdened with deceit, and unjuſt dealings, and corruptions. Hearken, hearken in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, how it cries for equity, and with ſighs and groans cries upon the Lord for mercy and equity, and the Lord doth often ſend his Angel to relieve the ſimple: for luſt and pride oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it, and it is burdened with it, and often tells thee <hi>All is vanity,</hi> which thy luſtful will and minde delighteth in, which is without, and which is in the firſt birth; and would have thee to hearken to equity, and within, and not to thy luſt, that thou mightſt have unity with God, and not with the world: for <hi>the whole world lies in wickedneſs,</hi> where equity cannot enter; it cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up and down the ſtreets: but hard hearts, and drunkards, and curſed ſpeakers, cozeners and cheaters, and thou high and lofty one, and whoremongers, and idolaters, and oppreſſors, and diſſemblers, ye all ſhut the door of Equity: when it cries to enter, there is no room for it amongſt theſe theeves: for ye all muſt be brought before the great Judge of heaven and earth, which deſpiſe Equity: The great Judge is coming, to render vengeance upon all that act contrary to Equity, and in your own knowledge, and out of your own mouthes ſhall ye be judged, in righteouſneſs: for he is righteous that judgeth, and hath ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>MEn bring up their children in natural Learning, to have natural Books, and Languages, as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew and Greek; and have the Schools of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> which they call the two Mothers of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118244:9"/>Divinity, which is Divinity: and ſo training up in the natural, lives up in the natural man, both in pride, in knowledge, in perſon, ſet up, called of men Maſter; and ſo with his books, and Learning which he got at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> he trades with others, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Languages, and tells people it is the Original, and ſaith he is ſent of Chriſt; which is the Whore and the Beaſt upon the waters, that is the people; and ſo all this is Witchcraft, Whoredom, Sorcery, Divining and Conjuring, Hypocriſie and Diſſembling, and was never ſent of Chriſt; for the Gift of God cannot be bought and ſold, but the letter; and Carnal ſells the Carnal, but the Word cannot be ſold, by which all things ſtand and remain.</p>
               <p>Another he ſtands up, and ſaith he is the Miniſter of Chriſt, which never was at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> but hath had ſome experience of the Truth taſted: and he is got up into notions, and fleed the Croſs: he goeth out and trades, and ſells his experiences, and ſaith he is gifted; which is falſe, for the gift of God is not to be bought and ſold for money. Now the Truth is not to be bought and ſold for money; but, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give.</hi> Truth was ſent forth without bag, or purſe, or ſilver, or ſcrip, or two coats, or a ſtick to defend it: for their weapons were ſpiritual; and all the others, which Chriſt hath not ſent forth, their weapons are carnal, they ride with their carnal ſwords, and run to a carnal Magiſtrate to defend them, and to get their carnal means of the poor people, which do not pay them: and thoſe Jeſus Chriſt never ſent forth. Where the pure light Chriſt is made manifeſt in Magiſtrate or People, it doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover them, and deny them. And the one he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118244:9"/>a Chriſt without, and the other he preacheth a Chriſt within. And he that preacheth Chriſt within, and he that preacheth Chriſt without, are both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; for they both have him in the notion; for he muſt be within, and not ſpeak. For where Chriſt is riſen and ſpeaketh, he denies him that ſpeaks a Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in the notion, and him that ſpeaks of him without in the notion, and all the earthly powers to uphold them, and none but God alone to uphold him in his ſtrength and power, by his own Spirit. And he that preacheth Chriſt without, he knows him not, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly takes him for a Clack, and the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to trade with them; like a Stage-player, which acts a Stage-play aloft, with Points, and Reaſons, and Uſes, and Authors, and old Fathers, and Tryals, and Mattens, and ſinging <hi>David</hi>'s quakings, cryings, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, prayers, and praiſes; and ſo act a Stage-play for money; and he that will give the moſt, thither he goes; and where they will not give him money, he will not act his Play there. And he that preacheth and ſaith Chriſt is within, he muſt be dumb, and not ſpeak; and the reaſon and the carnal part muſt ſpeak him, and the dumb is crucified. And he that ſpeaks him within, and he that ſpeaks him without, know him not with their carnal reaſon. Where he is riſen, and comes to be King, there he denies all the worlds ways, Diviners and Conjurers, and denies all the world, and reigns o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the corruption of man. To him alone be all glory, who reigns over all, and is King of Saints, King of Kings, Lord of Glory, bleſſed for ever. To whom be all Glory for ever. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Written by a friend of the Truth of the living God, to all whom it may concern.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118244:10"/>
               <p>THe Lord God of power is thundering, and uttering them forth againſt all you, and upon the top of all your Powers of Witchcraft, Charmers, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters, who live in your Sorcery, and Whoredom, and Witchcraft, and Myſtery of Iniquity. The Lord is riſen and riſing to threſh you down with an Iron rod. The weight of the Lords hand is upon you, and ſtretched over you; which goes to the Popes head. All bag and baggage muſt be taken. The Sword of the Almighty is drawn againſt all your Popiſh ways. Your Witchcraft and Whoredom is come up before the Lord, to hew down and trample. The Horſe is gone forth, Death, Death: All your Idols, all your Jewels, all your Pictures, all your Beads, earth to the earth. All your Chanters, and all your Charmers, will ſtand you in no ſtead. All your Counſellors will not hide you in the day of the Lords wrath. All your outſide knowledge of Angels, of the Apoſtles, of Chriſt, of <hi>Mary,</hi> will not ſave you, nor ſtand you in any ſtead. For the day of the Lords wrath is come among you; a day of Vengeance: the fire is kindling. All your Pictures, all your Croſſes and Crucifixes, muſt make a fire to burn you. The Lord hath ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his hand againſt you.</p>
               <p>Wo unto <hi>Rome,</hi> and all her Popiſh ways. Wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the Prieſts in <hi>England,</hi> who had the Popiſh Law. Ye Jeſuites, ye Inchanters, Myſtery of Wratchcraft;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118244:10"/>the Sword is drawn out againſt you, to cut you down. Ye high Ekens, which thought none had been able to make War againſt you; now is the hand of the Lord of hoſts upon you all, and his Army is gathering, and his Sword is drawn, which hath two edges, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him none ſhould eſcape. The Land ſhall be plain before his hoſt. The Lord hath ſpoken it. To you all, this is the word of the Lord. The hand of the Lord is ſtretched out againſt all the Adulterers and Idolaters; and the Sword of the Lord lies upon the Popes neck.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
